Guide to the Office of the President records, 1795-2007 RG0002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Presidents before 1927, 1795-1975, 2003; circa 1821-1927; Series 1; 6.25 Linear Feet 12 document boxes, 1 slim document box
  - Charles Herbert Stockton materials, 1910-1926; Series 1 Sub-series 8; 0.25 Linear Feet 1 slim document box
    Charles Herbert Stockton was made Acting President in May 1910. In June of that year the Attorney General made a preliminary report upon the financial affairs of the University and found that the expenses of the University had exceeded its income and endangered the endowment. A heavy mortgage was placed on the properties housing the Medical School and Hospital. President Stockton, during the early years of his administration served without compensation. He maintained a close scrutiny on all expenditures and laid the basis for a solid recovery for the University.
    Through the urging of Dr. Stockton, the Department of Arts and Sciences was moved in 1912 to 2023 G Street, the area that George Washington himself had selected as the site for "his" University. Foggy Bottom was established as the new central location. President Stockton's credentials could not have been better for the challenges that would confront the University. Perhaps his most significant qualification for guiding the University during World War I was his status as a retired Rear Admiral. As the United States drew ever closer to full involvement in the conflict, Stockton placed the University at the government's disposal. Also during the Stockton Presidency the Law School became co-educational, the College of Engineering and Mechanical Arts became the School of Engineering and the Summer Sessions were established.
    This sub-series consists of a single folder of correspondence related to the administration of the university, a photocopy of a biographical sketch of President Stockton, and a bound journal in which President Stockton kept records of the weather and events related to the administration of George Washington University for the first half of 1918.
    - Charles Herbert Stockton, Correspondence, 1910-1926 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Charles Herbert Stockton, Historical Sketch, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Charles Herbert Stockton, Journal, 1918 January 29 - June 10 (Box 8, Item 1)
      General note
      Entries by President Stockton, noting the weather, daily meetings, student enrollment and charges, receipts and disbursments.
  - William Collier records, 1915-1955, 2003; 1918-1920; Series 1 Sub-series 9; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
    The records from Presidents Collier and Lewis were transferred to the library from the office of the president's own archives in April 1980.
    The files primarily are arranged alphabetically by subject, with two folders of correspondence with university administrators at the beginning and the former vertical file and file of correspondence with Marvin at the end. The files remain in the arrangement in which they were received in the archives.
    William Miller Collier was president of George Washington University from 1918 to 1921. Collier was born November 11, 1867 in Lodi, New York, the son of Rev. Isaac H. and Frances Miller. He married Frances Beardsley Ross of Auburn, September 13, 1893. Collier died April 15, 1956. An alumnus of Hamilton College (A.B., 1889; A.M., 1892), Clinton, N.Y., and Columbia University Law School, Dr. Collier was a lawyer by profession and a recognized authority on Civil Service. He rose from law clerk to become referee in bankruptcy and president of the New York State Civil Service Commission (1899-1903). Dr. Collier wrote a number of books on law. He was a distinguished lecturer on international law and diplomacy for many years, both at New York University Law School and at the George Washington University.
    Dr. Collier served and was a friend of seven United States Presidents. He was the First Solicitor of the former Department of Commerce and Labor and then special assistant to the Attorney General in charge of antitrust cases under President Theodore Roosevelt, who later appointed him to be Minister in Spain (1905-09). In 1914, President Woodrow Wilson sent him to Norway to head the United States delegation at an international conference to frame a government for the island of Spitzenberg.
    President Collier assumed his duties at the University in the late summer of 1918 as the American involvement in Europe was reaching its highest point. A unit of the Student Army Training Corps and United States Naval Unit were established for the period of the war. In 1918 a special convocation was held for the first conferring upon a ruling prince of an honorary degree in the Nation's Capital. His majesty, Albert, King of the Belgians, received the honor. In 1921, having presided over the centennial celebration of the University, Collier resigned when President Warren G. Harding nominated him for an ambassadorship to Chile (where he served from 1921-28), and was instrumental in mediating a border dispute between Chile and Peru. Universities in both countries honored him for his part in the settlement.
    In the records from the presidency of William Collier we find for the first time the beginnings of a modern administrative filing system, though much of it has undoubtedly disappeared or been destroyed prior to its arrival in the archives. The files consist primarily of correspondence related to administration of the university, including the Student Army Training Corps during WWI.
    The sub-series also includes several files of materials collected about Collier following his presidencylater, including a vertical file and a file of correspondence with President Marvin.
    - William Collier, Correspondence with E.L. Kayser, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - William Collier, Correspondence with Dean Borden, undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 2, Folder 3)
    - William Collier, Centennial, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - William Collier, Dental School, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - William Collier, Fall Convocation, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - William Collier, Correspondence, 1920; 3 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 7, Folder 8, Folder 9)
    - William Collier, Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - William Collier, Hatchet & Cherry Tree, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - William Collier, Correspondence with Treasurer Holmes, undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 10, Folder 1, Folder 2)
    - William Collier, Honorary Degrees, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - William Collier, Dr. Hunter, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - William Collier, Medical School, 1918-1919 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - William Collier, Medical School Budget, 1919-1920 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - William Collier, Dr. Mess, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - William Collier, Military Organization, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - William Collier, Micellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - William Collier, Real Estate, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - William Collier, Senator, etc., undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - William Collier, STAC (Student Army Training Corps), 1918-1919 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - William Collier, STAC (Student Army Training Corps), 1918 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - William Collier, STAC (Student Army Triaining Corps), 1919 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - William Collier, STAC (Student Army Training Corps) Circular Letters, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - William Collier, STAC (Student Army Training Corps) Disbandment, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - William Collier, Scholarships, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - William Collier, Student Activities, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - William Collier, Trustees - McLaughlin - Thurston, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - William Collier, Trustees - Lisner - MacFarland, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - William Collier, Trustees - Tuckerman - Woodhull, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - William Collier, Correspondence, 1918-1921 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - William Collier, former vertical file, 1953, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - William Collier, Correspondence with Dr. Marvin, 1928-1955 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - William Lewis records, 1923-1927 and undated; Series 1 Sub-series 10; 1 Linear Feet 2 document boxes
    This sub-series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent name or subject, with the two general files of information about President Lewis at the end. The alphabetical files remain in the order in which they were received in the archives, which is presumably the order established by Lewis' office staff.
    William Mather Lewis, the eleventh president of George Washington University, served from 1923 to 1927. Lewis was born in Howell, Michigan on March 24, 1878, and moved with his family to Joliet, Illinois, where he received his elementary education. He attended high school in Galesburg, Illinois and graduated from Lake Forest College with an A.B. degree in 1900. He received his M.A. at Illinois College in 1902, where he also taught English literature. In 1903 he returned to Lake Forest College, where he taught until 1906, when he became head master at Lake Forest Academy. He resigned in 1913 and went abroad for two years to study English, French, and German school systems. Upon his return in 1915, citizens of Lake Forest elected him mayor, and he instituted a far-reaching "City Beautiful" project.
    During World War I he was executive secretary of the National Patriotic Societies. From 1919-21 he was director of the Savings Division of the United States Treasury, where he oversaw a national thrift campaign. In 1921 he became chief of the education service for the United States Chamber of Commerce, advising cities around the country how to improve their school curriculum, buildings, and equipment. "Spend as much money as possible for education, but make it pay a good dividend," was the backbone of his advice. In 1923 he was chosen as President of George Washington University. President Lewis was well known as a brilliant speaker and in demand by various groups. During his four-year presidency, a new gymnasium was erected and Mrs. Joshua Evans, Jr. was elected by the Alumni as the first woman member of the Board of Trustees. After leaving George Washington University Lewis assumed the presidency of Lafayette College in Pennsylvania. He died in 1945.
    This sub-series primarily comprises a set of alphabetical correspondence files from the Lewis administration, as well as two files of biographical and other information collected about Lewis.
    - William Lewis, Campaign for Funds A-Z, undated; 3 folder(s) (Box 12, Folder 4, Folder 5, Folder 6)
    - William Lewis, Campaign for Funds Executive Campaign Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - William Lewis, Campaign for Funds Special Gifts Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - William Lewis, Campaign for Funds Women's Committee, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - William Lewis, Council Meetings, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - William Lewis, D, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - William Lewis, Educational Organizations American Council on Education, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - William Lewis, Educational Organizations Association of Urban Universities, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - William Lewis, H, undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - William Lewis, Innauguration Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - William Lewis, K, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - William Lewis, Lawrence, Robert, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - William Lewis, Lecture Course, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - William Lewis, William Mather, 1923-1927 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - William Lewis, M, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - William Lewis, Oxford Debates, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - William Lewis, P-S, undated (Box 13, Folder 7, Folder 8)
    - William Lewis, Summer School, 1923-1924 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - William Lewis, Summer School Lectures, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - William Lewis, W, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - William Lewis, Washington Elm, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - William Lewis, Presidents, 1923-1924 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Former vertical file, 11/07/1923-09/23/1925 (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Cloyd Heck Marvin records, 1903, 1924-1969; 1927-1959; Series 2; 17.25 Linear Feet 34 document boxes, 1 slim document box
  This series is arranged in seven sub-series. The first six sub-series (Alphabetical correspondence files, Special events files, Publications, Accreditation files, University organization files, and Prizes and prize tea files) were established prior to the files' transfer to the archives, presumably by Marvin's own office staff. They are presented here in no particular order, although their contents remain in the order in which they were received. The final sub-series brings together files of additional materials about Marvin and his presidency by people outside the Marvin administration.
  Cloyd Heck Marvin was the twelfth President of the George Washington University, a position he held from 1927 to1959. The thirty-two years of Dr. Marvin's presidency is the longest in the history of the school. He was born August 22, 1889 in Findlay, Ohio. He moved with his family to Riverside, California in 1909, and graduated from high school there that year. After beginning his studies at Stanford University, he earned an A.B. degree (1915) and M.A. degree (1916) from the University of Southern California, and an M.A. (1917) and Ph.D. (1919) from Harvard. He served as a faculty member and dean at U.C.L.A. from 1919-22, and became president of the University of Arizona in 1922, at the age of 33. He served five years there before coming to GW in 1927.
  When he arrived, the "G Street high school," as some derided it, was crowded into about one square block, and had 109 full-time faculty and an enrollment of 5,478. Dr. Marvin reorganized the administration of the University, and with the assistance of the Board of Trustees he revamped and strengthened its financial structure so that at no time in his administration, even during the depression and the war years, was there a retrenchment through reduction in the size of the teaching staff or in faculty salaries. By the 1930s, the University had become well established in the Foggy Bottom area, and the institution had become a true urban university. By the time Marvin retired in 1959, the University had spread out to more than six times its old area, and the faculty and enrollment had doubled. Endowments were four times bigger and physical properties had increased eighteen fold. President Marvin died April 27, 1969 in Washington, D.C. His widow Dorothy Betts Marvin (whom he married in 1917) gave a naming gift of $1.5 million for the Cloyd Heck Marvin Student Center in 1971.
  The Marvin-era records of some administrative committees and councils may be found in the so-named subseries of records from the Elliott administration, where they were apparently maintained for historical information.
  This series represents a remarkably complete view of the functions of the Marvin administration, when compared to those of his predecessors. The files appear to remain structured and organized as they were within the president's office during the period of their active use. The series consists primarily of correspondence, though publications and reports also appear, particularly in the Publications and Accreditation files subseries.
  Additional details about the contents of each sub-series are provided at the sub-series levels, below.
  - Alphabetical correspondence files, 1927-1958 and undated; Series 2 Sub-series 1; 3.125 Linear Feet 6.25 document boxes
    The alphabetical correspondence files from Marvin's presidency were transferred to the library from the office of the president in April 1980.
    Files are arranged alphabetically by either correspondent name or subject.
    The alphabetical correspondence files contain incoming and outgoing correspondence from President Marvin. The correspondents are primarily external to the university, but the sub-series also includes memos to the faculty and administrators. The sub-series is not limited by topic and likely includes all issues relevant to his administration.
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, A, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Agriculture Department, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, American Association of University Professors, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, American Council on Education, 1949-1956 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, American Council on Education - Conference on College Degree Candidacy, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, American University, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Association of Oldest Inhabitants, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Auditorium Discrimination - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Auditorium Policy, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, B, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Civil Defense - The GWU Center, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Civil Defense - Washington Area Survival Committee, undated (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Columbian Women, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Community Chest - Relationship to D.C. Hospitals, 1933-1934 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Constitutional Review, The, undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, D, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Daughters of the American Revolution, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, D.C. Commissioners, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Mrs. Chauncey M. DePew, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, DePew - Chair in Public Speaking (Butler, Charles Henery), undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Dimock Estate, 1940-1941; 4 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 4, Folder 5, Folder 6, Folder 7)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, E-F, undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Faculty Club, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Foreign Service Review Course - school of government, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, G, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, George Washington Memorial Association, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Gradutate Record Examination, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Guzman, Humberto (Fricke), undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, H-L, undated; 4 folder(s) (Box 16, Folder 7, Folder 8, Folder 9, Folder 10, Folder 11)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Lisner Auditorium - G.W. Memorial Association Plaque, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, London University - Examination Center (Action of the Board of Trustees), February 14, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Mc-M, undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 17, Folder 3, Folder 4)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Maryland University Correspondence, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, National League of Masonic Clubs, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Masonic - Proposals for Endowing Chairs and Scholarships, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Eugene Mayer, Chair of Medicine - Gifts, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, N, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, National Institute of Public Affairs, undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, National Research Council, undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Mrs. Richard Norton (Donor of Portrait), undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Notices of Meetings, Board of Trustees, 1927-1949 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Notices of Faculty and Administrative Staff, 1928-1949 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, O, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Omicron Delta Kappa, undated (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Organization - General 2/21/51 Report to Facilities of GWU, undated (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, P, undated (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Pan American Union, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Patterson, Miss J. Pauline, undated (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Phillips, Miss Anna L., undated (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Questionnaires, 1927-1949; 4 folder(s) (Box 18, Folder 1, Folder 2, Folder 3, Folder 4)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, R, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Rankin, John O., Estate, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Rankin, John O., Correspondence, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Reserve Officers Training Corps, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Organized Reserve Corps Units (to be established at University), undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, S, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Saturday Evening Post - "Dr. Marvin's Genius Factory", undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Scottish Rite Scholarship, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Scottish Rite - New Age Article, 1957-1958 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Sigma Xi, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Simpson & Anderson Controversy, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Southern Conference, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, National Student Federation (Rule 6), undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, T, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Teague Bill of G.I. Benefits, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Television, Educational Correspondence, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Television, Engineering, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Television, Joint Commission on (also FCC Memoranda), undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Tompkins, Charles H. Gifts, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Tompkins, Charles H.; Engineering, School of, "Vault for the Future", undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Tompkins, Charles H.; Tompkins, Charles H., Company, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Tompkins Hall of Engineering, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, U, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, U.S.A.F. - Institute of Technology - Wright-Patterson A.F.B., undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, V-W, undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 20, Folder 5, Folder 6)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Ward, Lester, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, X Y Z, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Special events files, 1924-1957; Series 2 Sub-series 2; 1 Linear Feet Files total approximately 1 document box, but are spread across two different document boxes
    Arranged in reverse chronological order by date of event.
    The special event files contain information about a selected number of events that Marvin participated in while president of the university. The files may include materials such as the text of speeches and comments given at the events, programs, and other planning documents and correspondence relating to the event.
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Special Convocation - King of Morocco Honorary Degree ("In Camera"), November 27, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Special Convocation - President Luis Battle Berres, December 7, 1955 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Special Convocation - In Honor of Syngman Rhee, July 30, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Nihin University - President Bumpei Kure, Honorary Degree, 1953-1956 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Dedication of Chapin Hall, January 11, 1952 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Cloyd H. Marvin, Convocation - In Commemoration of Franklin Delano Roosevelt, April 13, 1945 (Box 20, Folder 14)